Bill Wiens

billwiens@gmail.com 503.689.3803 Seattle, WA 98102

Summary

I'm an experienced DevOps engineer who loves open-source technology. I'm a generalist; I like to delve into all parts of the stack. I design reliable and efficient systems with my skills in automation, deployment, monitoring, and cloud computing.

Experience

May 2012 - Sept 2014: DevOps Engineer at Smashing Ideas

- Worked with internal developers and client operations staff to provision infrastructure and enable rapid deployment for Python and PHP web applications and services.
- Used both Puppet and Chef to manage CentOS and Ubuntu servers, including physical servers and those virtualized in the cloud (AWS, Rackspace).
- Completed performance analyses to find bottlenecks and advised on/implemented fixes.
- Acted in a "firefighter" role to debug and fix unexpected system issues.
- Used a variety of monitoring and analytics tools (Nagios, Munin, Boundary, New Relic).
- Introduced the use of Vagrant to create disposable development environments and Jenkins for build automation.

August 2010 - May 2012: Developer at Smashing Ideas

- Administered a platform of 70+ international Drupal sites and led a team to overhaul and maintain them.
- Led initiatives to add Varnish, Memcached, and a CDN to our infrastructure.
- Trained new developers.
- Developed and documented process for tracking, testing, and deploying bug fixes and new features.
- Acted as a security liaison and provided a quick turnaround on critical security issues.

Sept 2009 - July 2010: Web Developer at Freelock Computing

- Developed web applications using the Drupal CMS.
- Focused on agile development using close collaboration with clients.
- Wrote custom PHP modules, used JavaScript and jQuery to create dynamic experiences, wrote custom SQL queries.

Nov 2009 - Feb 2010: Software Development Engineer at Qworky.com

- Worked with a small distributed team to create Qworky Meetings, a Ruby on Rails web-application featuring XMPP-based in-browser chat.
- Designed our development workflow utilizing Git and Capistrano for deployment.
- Architected and maintained an application stack based on Apache, OpenFire, and MySQL.

Feb 2009 - Sept 2009: Linux System Administrator at Freelock Computing

- Administered Ubuntu and Red Hat Linux servers for Freelock and clients.
- Performed maintenance and deployment of Drupal websites.
- Took charge of an initiative to document and consolidate Freelock's server infrastructure.
- Migrated internal services to a virtualized environment using VMware Server.

Technical Skills

- Capable of creating concise and elegant code in C++, Python, PHP, and Ruby.
- Well-versed in tools and frameworks such as Django, Fabric, Capistrano, and Vagrant.
- Knowledgeable in front-end web technologies such as HTML, CSS, and JavaScript.
- Almost a decade of experience with CentOS and Ubuntu Linux.
- Worked with Apache, Nginx, Gunicorn, Memcached, MySQL, PostgreSQL, and others.
- Expert with Git and Subversion.
- Superb problem-solving skills in hardware and networking.

Education

Willamette University in Salem, OR B.A., Computer Science — 2004–2008

Linköping University in Linköping, Sweden Study abroad program — 2007

Interests

- · Assembling and disassembling everything.
- The great outdoors.
- · Games of all sorts.
- · Collecting animated GIFs.
- Food, booze, and music.
- The intersection of technology and culture.

References

Available upon request.